my name is Jeffrey Stockbridge I'm in
currently in South Philadelphia and it
is snowing outside so my dad gave me my
first camera when I was 16 years old I
was a skateboarder and I started
skateboarding when I was 11 when you're
a skateboarder in the city it gives you
a lot of freedom to go into any
neighborhood you want looking for
interesting obstacles to skateboard on
and interesting tricks to do they
brought me to see different parts of the
city that I probably would have never
seen otherwise and having a camera with
me gave me even another reason to be
there
growing up in Maryland I wasn't far from
Philadelphia and only two hours away and
Philadelphia is and has been for a long
time the East Coast Capitol escape that
the impulse to skateboard in the park is
so strong it's like one of the best
places like to skate you know I mean
it's like skating paradise so I
naturally when I got out of high school
I moved to Philadelphia so I guess it
wasn't until my junior year the end of
my third year in college that I had
first started to create a body work that
had some serious and this to it so let
me break it down for you when I moved to
Philly
this was my first time really living in
a city and I lived in poorer
neighborhoods in West Philadelphia where
there were a lot of abandoned houses
each of these eminently hazardous
properties these hundred properties are
all a time bomb ready to go off and it
is only by the grace of God that they
don't go off on any particular day
take a look at this abandoned Shack
behind me for three years it was on the
city's list of most dangerous buildings
slated to be destroyed this past fall I
was curious I wanted to know where these
houses came from why were they abandoned
you know what happened to the people
that had lived there so I started to
investigate that it was remarkably easy
to gain access sometimes you could walk
right in the front door sometimes a
window would be open you could go in the
back door or a cellar door and I would
basically find a way to get inside these
abandoned houses and I would make
photographs of the interiors very
interested in capturing a sense of the
memory of the past occupants who lived
there I also found incredible artifacts
left behind old letters family
photographs journal entries by the
people who had once called this
structure a home so it was through
photographing these abandoned houses for
years I did that for maybe four or five
years and I had met a lot of people
during that time and at first I you know
honestly I was kind of scared of them
I didn't really want to have any contact
with the people that I was meeting
inside these abandoned houses they were
homeless they were addicted to drugs I
didn't necessarily feel safe in their
presence after a while that all changed
I started to grow more comfortable
talking to the people that I was running
into right
yeah I was born and raised here at 1965
making connections with people in the
neighborhoods that I was photographing
Oh God's Way tell me if I can if I think
I can do these drugs again and shoot
heroin in my arm it's like he gives me a
little sign look down on your arm you
idiot that's like me with these tattoos
and I realized that hey here's a third
element of the project that I totally
forgot about the actual people that are
still living in the neighborhood that
everybody else a band my children I'd
have to look them in the eye before I
actually brought it up to my face
I got them right here when I stopped
drinking in o-fag I had met a woman
named Millie who was selling her body
inside of a crack house she was
literally going to different crack
houses around West Philadelphia in
search of people with drugs that she
could exchange sex for drugs and I found
her story to just be harrowing it was
incredible I mean I can't tell you why
Millie decided to talk to me you're
gonna have to ask her who knows when the
last time was that somebody asked her
about her life or asked her where she
came where she grew up
or how she survived you know I think
it's as simple as saying that you know I
was you know a disruption to her daily
routine and that may have been
interesting to her maybe that's it I
don't know I'm speculation so I
we hung out one afternoon I photographed
her while the Sun set she told me her
life story and it was this single
interaction that really spurred me in a
new direction and was the reason that I
started to visit Kensington and start
the new body war Kensington blues
when I'm walking down the street in
Kensington and I'm interested in making
photographs I'm just walking the streets
and I'm just stopping I'm saying hi to
people I'm talking to them it's never
about hey can I take your photograph
it's always hey I was going today you
know what's going on just trying to have
a conversation with people like they're
human beings not like I'm after
something not like I'm only here for one
reason because I'm not the first time we
met I had been clean for almost two
years I did 13 months in jail and I was
in a recovery house and as soon as I
finished probation relapsed and you know
I probably been out on the street for
maybe two and a half months at this
point back with a pimp
and I was extremely disappointed in
myself but at the same time like I had
told you before I never really expected
myself to even make it to this age you
know which was 30 whatever and expected
myself to fully wind up as just an old
junkie not like you enough to overdose
and die
I remember when you approached me I had
heard about you from other other girls
and I remember when you approached me
thinking you know of course the first
thing I think when somebody says I'd
like to take a photo of you my first
thought is you want to take you know
dirty photos of me not this and
interview me and actually care about you
know what was going on in my life and
how I wound up there etc I liked what
you were doing I was kind of I don't
know if excited is the right word but
yeah I was excited that somebody was
looking at me as a human being and not
somebody that sticks a needle in their
arm every day a nuisance to society I
always been interested in telling my
story on my computer I probably have
maybe almost 10 you know beginnings of
you know my own book I'd like to write
about my life you know I've been written
about several times by by this point and
for someone to tell me that after seven
years they still think about me and
impact that my story you or me as a
person has had on their life to the
point to where they remember you know so
many details about me that they want to
write about me is
of course flattering and a good end dad
okay but makes me realize that you know
I I want my story to be told and I would
like to tell it myself you know
I think that that makes the people that
I'm photographing a meeting want to
share their story for that specific
reason they want to be remembered and
Krista says the exact same thing she
doesn't know when she gets into a car if
she's gonna get back out of that car
she's hopping you know in the
automobiles with strangers turning
tricks for twenty forty sixty dollars a
date you know there's a lot of
unpredictability there and I think that
that was one of the main reasons that
she wanted to share her story with me I
mean that's the scar right here
you know guy picked me up beat the shit
out of me split my face up and broke
three bones in my face and basically
said to me the reason I picked on
someone like you is because no one
noticed no one would notice if you
disappeared and it's true and sadly you
know it's true and so yeah absolutely
you know that play a part in it kind of
like well you know what I better get
some of this stuff out there in case I
get into the wrong car one of these days
and then maybe there'll be something
left behind of being of how I felt you
know of what was really going on
any person with a you know a little bit
of knowledge of photography or just
representation in general would
recognize that a photograph of somebody
at one point in time their life doesn't
need to be a statement for who that
person is for their entire life you know
like this photograph is just
representing a moment in time okay and
that's what Krista talks about a moment
in time she likes knowing that she likes
being able to look at photographs of
what she used to look like at a certain
moment in time so that she can remember
who she was then because she's changing
and she's not the same person she was
that she's completely different I have
always always wanted any kind of photo
from when I was using in my life at one
point I tried to get copies of all of my
mug shots throughout the years and the
Philadelphia Police Department told me
that no I could not have copies because
my image was the property of the
Philadelphia Police Department and I
said well that photo may be your
property but it's still my image I'm not
asking you for the originals I'm asking
you for even a photocopy of it just
because I like yeah I like to see the
progression I like to it's a reminder to
me yeah like this like I don't want to
look like this again you know I mean
like it's just a reminder she's grown a
lot
it doesn't just because she's gone back
to using here or there doesn't mean that
you know that she is just an addict for
life I mean to get clean it takes time
you have to be stumble when you're
walking
Lu you that's part of the process so I
never feel like when I'm photographing
people on the street who are deep in
their addiction as if I'm forever
defining them as an addict I don't feel
that way at all I feel as though I'm in
a unique position to get to know
somebody when they are in a very
vulnerable state I'm in a unique
position to spend time with somebody
when they need somebody to spend time
with to tell you the truth no I do not
pay my subjects Kensington Blues is a
collaborative effort between myself and
the people that I photograph everyone I
photograph is a willing participant
they want their stories to be heard or
they want their image to be out there
you know they'll everyone I photograph
has different reasons for why they want
to do this you know sometimes it's they
actually just want a picture of
themselves that I could bring back to
them in a week sometimes they hope that
the picture will make it on the internet
so that their loved ones know that
they're still alive that they still
exist
it becomes very complex particularly an
environment like a street based
community in street based communities
are hustling communities those people
who are existing in those communities
have to find diverse ways to survive and
have to find diverse ways to meet their
diverse needs and some of those needs
can include life controlling drug
addictions and so I can imagine the
challenge when a photographer like
jeffery comes to that community and is a
part of that community and makes images
based in that community that it might be
really difficult for the members of that
community to accept that they are his
commercial venture in some senses you
know people think you know you're gonna
make millions of dollars off of this
book you know I can't believe he's
selling this book for $60 and he's only
giving 2% to
prevention point or whatever it is and
you know me trying to explain to people
you know like what he did this on his
own like he probably lost money doing
this so if there's ever a situation that
somebody reaches out and they're upset
about something I want to talk to them
you know I'm happy I am happy to have
that conversation with anybody I
photographed I really do
I mean I want to I want to feel as
though that I'm in a position to be like
hey like look this is this is kind of
like an education let me explain
something to you you want to know how
much the book cost me $45,000 cost me
$45,000 you no matter how many years of
my life I spent photographing this stuff
about ten thus far okay film and
processing and time and effort
everything all told I will never break
even you know I have probably would
express cynicism over people with life
controlling drug addictions and people
who are experiencing homelessness and
people who are working in street by sex
work being the continued subject of
documentary photographers but the
project has definitely endeared itself
to me because of the longevity of
commitment because of the fact that
Jeffrey is clearly not entirely resolved
in his methodological approach the fact
that he is trying to incorporate
people's own experiences in such a
rigorous way the whole especially in the
media the whole debate about whether
addiction is
a disease or a choice I'm I'm a drug
addict I'm a person that if I have a
drink I can't stop and so it would be
following your ideology that I'm
choosing to do that that I'm choosing
exactly my not my ideology is my belief
yes you do choose this is the stigma
that people with substance use disorders
face every single day the only way to
solve the drug problem is through
toughness when I was in China and other
places by the way I said mr. president
do you have a drug problem
no no we do not I said what do you
tribute that to well the death penalty
is something that I can't help or am I
just a scumbag am I just you know saying
fuck you everybody that cares about me
we have this disproportionate focus on
addiction in the media that is when we
have the vast majority of people who use
drugs do not meet criteria for addiction
but yet that's where our focus is why do
we have this disproportionate focus the
drugs that we're talking about our drugs
like crack cocaine heroin even in dma or
summative recreational drugs when we
talk about drugs in our popular culture
almost eat immediately the refrain is
addiction now the thing that the
listener should know is that the vast
majority of people that use any of those
drugs are not addicted so you only have
about 10 to 25 percent of the people who
use any of those drugs who will become
addicted so that means that most people
use these drugs are not addictive if
most of the people who are using these
drugs are not addicted then why in the
hell do all of the movies or the vast
majority of the movies that you see
about drugs deal with addiction
well because addiction is sexy and you
watch it's a lot less sexy to say watch
a movie about someone who uses heroin on
the weekend and then goes to work on
Monday and Tuesday whenever
they're scheduled to go to work and they
handle all of their responsibilities
that that would be a boring movie so you
have addiction because addiction is more
sexy or sexier and sex
here terms like the functional attic or
the functioning addict that's a misnomer
there's no such thing if someone is
functioning and they are not having any
problems with their drug use they're not
an addict addiction is defined by these
social and behavioral disruptions simply
because somebody is using crack cocaine
and their function doesn't make them an
addict for we can think about people who
drink alcohol on a regular basis we
don't call them functional addicts or
functional alcoholics we particularly in
the UK we call those people citizen I
have seen local media clips where Fox
News drives up and down Kensington and
they're filming underneath the tunnels
and they are portraying the situation
like like a safari our Hank Flynn took a
trip to camp scene 10 today that's where
some longtime residents are fed up with
this that is a heroin needle lying on
the side of a street right next to a
school
Jerri Mariner says he'd never leave
Kensington he raised his family there
but look at these pictures he took he's
sick and tired of the heroin trade
happening right on his stoop the selling
the using the prostitution this is it
he's at his wits end I took the trash
out two weeks ago and there's a dude
later my trash I mean it's where he
belongs really and that's my opinion
I mean people feel sorry for his people
I don't they're shooting it from their
car window I mean this isn't journalism
they're too scared to get out of their
car and talk to these people they
wouldn't know how to talk to these
people because the guy running the show
is wearing a buttoned up blue shirt and
he's already got his mind made up about
who these people are that type of
coverage in the media is exactly why I
do what I do because I think that that's
bullshit and I need to fight back
against that kind of stuff
we're not looking at more pictures of
recovery because we're still in a crisis
mode America has an insatiable appetite
for prescription opioids opioids are now
the biggest drug epidemic in American
history
Time magazine just put out a piece with
James Nachtwey
you know they hired a war photographer
to photograph a war as they saw it this
is an epidemic and when war is happening
you tend to see photographs of battle
not of victories maybe its inherent to
the way the media works as a tool for
social change I think a lot of people
would presume that showing how horrible
a situation is would be the most
effective way to try to help a scenario
and I did that myself for a number of
years but now I think it's most
important that I show that recovery is
possible and prove to people that you
can come back from an addiction I think
that that will prove to be equally as
effective because it's a significant
part of the truth it's a significant
part of the story that we've been
overlooking you know I can see that over
the period of time that he was there
that he was really learning how to tell
a story like this in a non stereotypical
way or in a way that transcended some of
those photographers you know heroic
author and subject as poor person that
needs to be saved
Tropes and I think as a you know as a
respectful portrayal of people who are
these kinds of experiences that we might
look down upon in society this project
is is significantly meaningful because
it it doesn't just treat them like they
are these physical props for selling
some sort of fantastic idea that he is
you know the intrepid photojournalist
showcasing misery perfectly beautifully
and it holds much more weight for me now
as a project than it did when I was just
seeing these kinds of images on
Instagram which i think is a poor
platform for project like this for me
being involved in this has been a
positive thing I like I said earlier I
you know like what you're doing I
thought it was a great idea
and I still do and I like kind of like
proud to be a part of it and like proud
to be a part of something where
someone's trying to tell our side of the
story
that's the goal ultimately to humanize
the situation that they're in because we
as a society have heard way too long
been dehumanizing these people been
demonizing these people been declaring
drug addicts as morally corrupt and
that's bullshit
you